howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
this is another in our extra koban 19
related mini podcasts
today's guest is michelle gurbin a
physics professor at the University of
Maryland College Park campus and
external faculty at the Santa Fe
Institute she's also one of the
strongest researchers in the area of
network science that I know of
and I've asked her to come on today to
talk a little bit about networks and
network propagations of Epidemiology and
what we have to think about on the
backside of the curb in terms of dynamic
responses to manage this disease on the
network Michelle take it away why don't
you talk to us a little bit about the
very basics of network science how
diseases propagate on a network and how
changes in the nature of the network
such as through social distancing can
change the dynamics of network
propagation of a disease thanks Jim for
having me here I am delighted to be here
to talk about applying network science
to this pandemic that we're experiencing
you know what's interesting for me from
a modeling perspective is how much the
general public is starting to learn
about mathematical modeling so that's
really exciting to me to see news
articles in The Washington Post's in the
New York Times talking about these si
are models susceptible infected
recovered and talking about modeling
parameters and quantities like are not
so that's probably what some of you have
seen a bunch of the news are not is the
average number of people infected when
one person gets effect infected and this
is
at the start of the disease before you
have any herd immunity and herd immunity
another term you've probably heard is
something where a lot of people who have
contracted the disease cancel that can
slow down the spread because there
aren't so many susceptibles so let's go
back so that's some of the basics of you
know epidemics 101 but epidemics 101
really thinks about a fully mixed
population so every person is sort of
equally likely to interact with every
other person they have a certain number
of connections on average and everyone
has about the same number of connections
so what's important from a network
science perspective is to think about
heterogeneity in the connection patterns
between people so one of the most
important heterogeneity is degree
distribution so some people have huge
numbers of connections while most people
have lower kind of more average numbers
of connect or more typical numbers of
connections just a few get strong
connections and that really changes the
spreading pattern so if you consider a
network where everybody has the same
number of connections compared to a
network where they're the same total
number of connections in the system but
some people have a much bigger share of
those connections so consider those two
networks the first homogeneous network
and the second heterogeneous network so
it turns out if you do the math
spreading on the heterogeneous network
is much more rapid and you end up with a
much greater fraction of the population
infected so the reason being is that
those people who have a high number of
connections they're likely to
the disease and then because they have a
high light high number connections
they're also likely to spread the
disease really quickly so this is one of
the parts that's not mentioned so much
in this great news coverage about
mathematical modeling but not only do we
have to think about our nacht and the
average properties of the network but we
have to think about the heterogenous
properties of the network and that's
where like closings schools comes in as
it is important because schools are a
big source of heterogeneity right
because school children interact really
strongly with it one another you have
it's kind of like a source of giving
people a lot of connections and so
closing these large things shutting down
big conferences part of that
intervention strategy is not to really
change the average properties but to cut
off that high end that tail end of the
distribution which is so responsible for
spreading so like for instance at a
conference with a thousand people who
are jammed into a room and are shoulder
to shoulder in the hospitality suite
afterwards
man that's a mixing bowl for viruses
big-time that's very different than sort
of the average interactions that we
might have on the street that that what
you're getting at
absolutely absolutely and so these there
can be two ways that this happens
because we have these highly clustered
interactions like conferences or because
we might have individuals that we would
call super spreaders who just go around
and are connected to so many people so
it's those that tail end that we really
want to control in our network type
interventions and are not one way to
think about the network science part of
this is to realize that on average your
friends have way more friends than you
do this is the friendship paradox and
network science and I think it's like
the first thing that you should learn if
you're trying to wrap your mind around
network
science says hey more about that I
remember reading about that early on
when I started digging into Network
science back in the early double lots
when I was going what how could that
possibly be true and then I work through
the math and I go yep for the average
person it's true could you run through a
simple example or illuminate that for us
a little bit sure I mean so so we all
think of ourselves as average and you
know we probably think of our friends as
average and so our friends are just like
us
right but consider Facebook for example
if you go and if you're on Facebook and
you look at what your number of friends
are and you look through all your
friends and find out their average
number of friends probably that average
is gonna be a lot higher than your own
number of friends and the reason is
because an average person in the network
you take the whole network you pick a
person at random you look at that
person's number of friends that's
different than following a random link
so picking a random one of your own
friends by following a link from you to
them
that link is followed preferentially by
their number of connections so because
there are some people who have so many
more connections you're way more likely
to be connected to somebody who has lots
of connections so then when you take a
step back and look at it the average
number of connections of your friends
you really expect that to be a lot
higher than the average number of
connections of an individual or the
number of connections that you have that
makes actually makes perfect sense when
you think about it from that way and
that's one of the things why network
science was such a huge contribution to
the intellectual working capital the
human race is that it produces very
actionable insights such as that that
are not intuitive yeah absolutely and I
think that that's a first way for people
to understand network science and to
realize oh when we're thinking about
these epidemiological models we just do
everything at the population average
level we're missing a lot of important
elements that really change
behaviors of the whole system and the
course of disease spread and I'm really
glad that we have a number of people
particularly in our Santa Fe Institute
community who are bringing advanced
epidemiological modeling with a network
understanding on top of it because you
know that provides as a very different
view rather than using these population
averages because you now to address a
little bit about how things like social
distancing either you know low end
social distancing like staying six feet
apart and more radical such as stay at
home orders how they change the literal
nature of the network and what impact
they are likely to have on the spread of
the disease that's a really good
question and there are a couple ways in
which they change the nature of the
spreading pattern so in these Network
models of disease spread you have a lot
of different parameters not only do you
have the network structure who's
connected to whom but you also have
parameters of the dynamics of the
disease the probability of transmission
along an edge so this staying six feet
apart from from one another if you still
are going about and interacting with the
same people like you're going to work
but you're staying far apart from one
another that's really changing the
probability of spreading between people
now it's also in part changing the
network because it's giving you fewer
opportunities to interact kind of
casually with people you might interact
with in a normal situation but what
really changes the network is these
lockdown situations where you're staying
at home you're completely reducing the
number of connections you have so not
only have you changed the probability of
transmission but you've changed the
network topology yep and so for instance
if we think about our relationships with
everybody we know it's a link between
let's say you and me and if the nature
of the link right now is you and I going
out to have dinner
at a restaurant we were sitting 18
inches apart the dynamics of how the
disease spreads probabilistically is one
thing if you and I are talking over zoom
it's entirely different so if instead of
doing this by zoom we did it face to
face we would be changing the nature of
propagation on the network exactly okay
and so that each one of these
essentially is changing the property of
the link we stop we don't stop knowing
people so our social graph in some sense
is still unchanged but the properties of
the graph the properties of each link
change as we social distance right and I
like to think about it as we have you
know our underlying social interaction
Network and then we have a subset of
that network the network along which the
transmission can spread so if you if
we're we have a social connection but
that connection is only being realized
virtually that's not a potential link
for spreading right and as people switch
from physical presence to virtual
presence I'm thinking in my head of
nodes and lengths you know the nature of
the links changes it now becomes
impossible for you know Jim to give
Michele Corcovado face meeting to a zoom
meeting and the more of those that
change literally the propensity to
propagate on the network changes very
considerably and another thing that we
really have to think about is that the
networks adapt in response to the
spreading patterns now one thing I think
that we as a community have been doing
pretty well is cutting down the number
of visits to doctors offices where you
have questionable symptoms and you might
then then healthy people who might get
the disease at a doctor's office so
there have been various policy
suggestions call your doctor from home a
move to move to telemedicine instead of
in-person visits because you know what
happens is when people are sick they go
to the doctor
and maybe they're sick with coronavirus
but maybe they're sick with a common
cold and then you know if you they're
all meeting especially this is a high
density of people who have kovat 19 in a
small space that really increases the
transmission so I think that's one thing
we've actually been doing right is
keeping people from going directly to
the doctor's office and trying to cut
off some of the spread that happens in
that way and this is of courses for
people who have just mild symptoms I'll
give you a perfect examples we talked
about pre-roll on the show my daughter's
like 25 weeks pregnant and
fingers-crossed been a very healthy
non-problematic pregnancy and her and
her doctor negotiated changing many of
her normal check-in visits from in
office to telemedicine for exactly that
reason the you know the benefit of a
routine office visit for a healthy
pregnancy is not zero but it's not huge
compared to a telemedicine and the risk
is significant so the math works out do
telemedicine right on the other hand if
she were to have a complication sheet of
course go to the doctor or the hospital
because at that point the the risk
reward works the other way and you know
so humans are smart we're you know a
smart adaptive agents and we are making
those changes again as we talked about
in the pre-roll both of us are now using
order in advance pick up at the grocery
store quarantined the food in a cooler
for a day etc and that's sort of
bottom-up self-organizing modifying the
network you know my relationship to my
grocery store is now a much less
powerful vector for viral spread right
absolutely i but I do wonder about some
of these changes have they gone far
enough I mean certainly there we need
our health care workers to keep going
you need our grocery workers to keep
going but are we putting enough measures
in to protect those people because they
are interacting with so many people
every day and what else can we do to
change the
transmission parameters to help protect
them also you know I kind of luckily
removed from manufacturing processes and
things like that but are the plants that
are manufacturing these goods what are
what are the network properties of the
individuals who are doing this important
work during this time and how can we
protect them better yeah and of course a
lot of that a different topic but
something you know near and dear to a
complexity science perspective is
unfortunately our hyper capitalist
short-term money on money return Society
has engineered everything for efficiency
and not for robustness you know for
instance we know these plagues are
coming look at the the data on
respiratory illnesses in the number of
cases and if you assume a fat tail
distribution which certainly seems
reasonable something like this is very
predictable to have happened someone who
was thinking in terms of robustness and
complexity would have stockpiled
billions of face masks right you know
tens of thousands of ventilators body
suits and so these issues of our health
care workers having to expose themselves
and a lot of them are heroes I mean my
sister-in-law is a nurse practitioner
and a heroic medical person who is
putting her life on the line literally
every day to help her patients I would
have felt a hell of a lot better and we
actually you know sent her masks and
things like that my brother sent her
some masks and you know if we've been a
smart robust and resilience thinking
society we would have prepared for this
right absolutely and right now that
could be a big weakness that we have in
our system because that's a point rate
so while everything else is closed down
it's these mega centers like hospitals
where there is a big possibility for
continued spread of the disease and if
we're not we don't have enough equipment
to make those precautions we're not
cutting off that tail like we need to
yea Lantern as you would say from the
network perspective those are you know
hi mixing nodes with a high propensity
of sick people right so just what you
don't want absolutely
another thing that I seen recently and
this is not related to my expertise in
network science so but I think it's an
interesting feature that's not been
included and a lot of the modeling is
the level of exposure that people have
so you know healthcare workers they can
get much hotter they can be exposed to
much higher doses of the virus as
compared to somebody who gets it from a
surface and as I've read again on expert
in this that how sick you get for many
types of viruses is strongly correlated
with that level of exposure so it's also
something we can be we should be taking
into account yes in fact a mini podcast
like we are publishing today from Robin
Hanson
we discuss in considerable detail dose
response and what might seem paradoxical
guidance that comes from that you know
for instance he's famous I kind of
classed and he talks about you know
maybe young people should voluntarily
get the illness be paid a small premium
for doing so and be given a card that
shows that are immune and maybe people
shouldn't shelter-in-place at home
because if one person in the house gets
it the dosage level in the house is
going to be very high so you know that's
an area that I'd like to see some of our
modelers you know hop on thinking about
this dose response possibility and maybe
it produces some you know non-intuitive
ways of responding yes and and you also
mentioned something that's really
important and part of the next step out
of this quarantine situation which is
knowing who's who had the infection
right so a lot of these different
strategies like you know getting the
virus which I'm not sure is good
strategy I'm not condoning that at the
moment but a lot of these different
strategies are predicated on knowing who
was infected and who wasn't so I think
that that's going to be a really
important part in designing our way out
of this after it you know if we are
successful in flattening the peak which
it seems like there is a good effort in
this area that these the you know
quarantine efforts are making a
difference but then what's next and how
can we plan for what's next without the
ability to test who's had the who's had
the disease or not
ah that's exactly right that's a good
time to transition to the second topic
which is managing the back side of the
curve that's now where all my attention
is in terms of actual work trying to
figure out what guidance to give to
government not-for-profits etc and I
feel like we're way behind the curve on
managing the backside of the curve and
it's going to be more difficult require
more you know a more aggressive
intellectually deep mindset than
managing the front side which has been
you know essentially fairly
straightforward break the network smash
the the curve doing the dance on the
back side is going to be very very
tricky if we're going to avoid the
historical second peak you know in the
famous influenza of 1918 which is
probably closest to in magnitude the
second peak you know four or five six
months later killed more people in the
first peak and there are ideas about how
we you know be much more dynamic on our
social distancing so we can take it off
in some places and bring it on in others
but that's gonna require data and
dynamic decision-making could you talk a
little bit about the you know the
network science and any thoughts you
have on managing the back side of the
curve until we have a vaccine that is
such an important question and as you
mentioned so much harder to answer so
from a mathematical modeling perspective
whether we're doing this like mixed
fully mixed population assumption or
whether we're adding in some of the
details of the network structure and the
heterogeneity is where some people have
lots of connections but most people have
a lower number so regardless of what
approach you take in the beginning it's
much easier to capture this because you
can make
something that almost everybody is
susceptible right and then as many as a
significant fraction of your population
gets infected with this and then
recovers modeling that side of things is
much harder and it's much harder in this
scenario when you have the hidden
variables that you don't know the states
of individuals whether they're they've
recovered or not or whether they were
never infected and so the mathematical
modeling is more complicated because for
two reasons you can't just consider
everybody to be susceptible and put the
name really harder part of connecting
mathematical modeling with intervention
strategies is you need to know what
class each of your people the
individuals are in are they still
susceptible or are they recovered and
now hopefully as we've heard enough of
that you know there is evidence that
they should be immune at least for a
while
yep and again this is multi-dimensional
analysis with unfortunately our society
ain't great at and you know we need to
have disease testing to catch people
with symptoms to crack down on them
quickly after the fact and as you point
out the immunity testing would be huge
to you know certify people to work in
dangerous virally dangerous frontline
physicians you know wouldn't it be great
if there were a ID certificate that said
I am immune and let those people go back
to work as uber drivers and working as
the store clerks etc and the other thing
is this monitoring so that we can bring
our resources to bear and I will say
there's one hopeful part of this is I've
been thinking about the network dynamics
let's say the smashing the curve works
we see a crash in the number of new
cases to gets down to a very low number
in late June and early July but we ramp
up testing then when the inevitable
hotspots reflet first and we'll hit one
and yet we built up this big reserve of
ventilators and
you know 15-minute test equipment we
should be able to mobilize them very
rapidly if necessary have the Marine
Corps fly men on helicopters and swarm
these new hot spots with 15-minute tests
you know with anybody testing etc and if
we need to shut them back down again
maybe it's just a County in a little
County in West Virginia that somehow
never had any disease at all so has no
immunity somehow somebody visits from
someplace get started flares up but if
we do a high enough level of testing you
know we'll be able to detect it early
and because we've already mobilized all
the equipment and stuff we can fly it in
and squash it but to do that requires a
warfighting data-driven model driven
mentality which so far is only slowly
spinning up absolutely I mean it really
has to be an organized effort so two
things that you touched on which really
I think are worth emphasizing and
thinking about more no I love this idea
of doing antibody testing you know there
is a little bit of a concern that people
who want to go back to work will
intentionally get the virus so that they
can now be card-carrying certified
recovered so that's something to worry
about and then another thing is to think
about the timing to use some of these
mathematical network based models to
really time the intervention strategies
and the social distancing requirements
at various times because what I suspect
on the backside of the curve also as it
was in the front side of the curve you
need to start changing people's behavior
before it looks bad absolutely or you
know the hospital system is overwhelmed
it's kind of hard to convince people to
change their behavior when things aren't
looking too bad so the timing of those
strategies is something that we really
need this combination of data analysis
and mathematical modeling to get right
yeah in fact just Aflac told me
I did the other day I can't find it on
the internet but she said that Paul
Romer was suggesting that it was worth
economically worthwhile to do was at 20
million tests a day so that we had
essentially instant information on any
flare-up so we're not waiting for you
know hospitals to be overrun but we find
in this county in West Virginia three
cases where there had been none for you
know six months and then we immediately
marshal the resources to squash it so
it's a you know you have modeling you
and you have data and you have the
ability to instantly respond and you
don't wait for weeks to go by for these
massive for these high-volume signals to
occur it's kind of an interesting idea
and I think you say it would cost three
hundred fifty billion dollars or
something but it'd be money well spent
so I think this kind of thinking is what
managing the back side of the curve is
going to be all about right absolutely I
hadn't thought about how that investment
might be really sensible from from an
economic payoff certainly from from an
ability to change the backside of the
curve absolutely it's gonna change
things and so I think it is a good
investment because by waiting and having
to quarantine and shut so many things so
many industries down it's a huge
economic impact but if we could have
really large-scale testing I mean it
would be very costly but it's great you
know to really see that analysis done to
see the economic benefits of that and I
look at the stock market alone how much
does it lost six trillion dollars
something like that and that's a you
know two hundred million two hundred
billion dollar year investment in
absolutely ubiquitous testing be
damn cheap to get our economy back to
work and as this kind of thinking
informed by modeling and exactly the
kind of network analysis combined with
epidemiology that we've been talking
about is what we need to be driving
whoever's in charge of thinking through
the strategy on the
backside of the curve and I wonder if we
could get companies involved like big
companies involved in this somehow to
say well you guys could send your full
workforce back to work if you agree to
pay for the testing yep frankly I've
been you know writing down business
ideas that this epidemic produces and
one of the ones near the top of the list
is a business that does nothing but
certify people to be for their immunity
and so a company could hire this company
you know rut go four hundred dollars per
employee to certify them as immune and
of course we have to have some caveats
tests aren't always accurate but if you
wanted to be more accurate you have them
tested twice right and we'll cart charge
you $200 and that will take the you know
basically the product of the error rates
so the error rate goes way down and they
also want to certify you also want the
company to monitor people who are
susceptible and continually monitor them
so it would be nice for them to be able
to go back to work too but we're trying
to guarantee a pretty safe environment
and to do this we keep testing the
susceptibles all the time yeah that's
the Paul Romer army 20 million tests a
week a day I think it was it some crazy
number but you're basically constant
surveillance everywhere so it's
relatively safe to go back to your
office as long as you know that if Sally
at the other end of your floor is got
the disease even though she's
pre-symptomatic and it's then told she
has to go quarantine for 15 days your
risks go way way down and if you know if
you're young and healthy it probably
makes sense to go back to work so again
you know thinking holistically about
networks propagations interventions
testing mobilization I believe that if
we did this right we could manage the
back side of the curve so that we did
not get a second peak until the vaccine
gets here but it will require a very
fancy dance to do it and I sure the hell
hope the powers that be are able to
organize a set of talent skills analysis
and action taking sufficient to do
it's doable and it will allow our
economy to restart it'll save probably
at least as many deaths and disabilities
as have happened from the first wave but
it's going to require smarter footwork
than we've seen on the front side I
totally agree the backside is the
challenge that we all need to put our
minds to now okay well thank you
Michelle this has been a wonderful
episode exactly what I was hoping but
before we sign off I'd like you to tell
our audience about a zoom based course
that you guys are offering on network
epidemiology so I direct the combined
program at the University of Maryland
combined stands for computation and
mathematics in biological networks so
network epidemiology is an important
focus within the field of biological
networks and when we shifted to an
online environment I thought okay well
I'm not my combining fellows to stay in
touch so let's do a little series on
network epidemiology but then I thought
well if we're gonna do an online series
there are a lot of people who might want
to learn about this so why not have a
bigger reach so then we partnered with
the Vermont complex system Center Santa
Fe Institute sent out a bunch of
announcements for us and we got a whole
bunch of people involved in this online
series on understanding and exploring
network epidemiology and the time of
coronavirus so this is a four week
series meeting once a week we have
tutorials and seminars but then we have
discussion sections and we have people
sign up to participate in group projects
and so they're all self-organizing on a
slack site so the live online sessions
are already oversubscribed
had many more excellent dedicated
applicants than we could accommodate but
we want true we want these resources to
reach anyone who is interested so we're
putting everything on our YouTube
channel so you can get to our YouTube
channel from the main combined website
combined is combined UMD edu you can
also google combined UMD and find those
videos we had an excellent tutorial
yesterday introducing us to network
epidemiology by Laurent Abair Dufresne
from the University of Vermont who's
done some really excellent work on
network epidemiology in general and also
on coronavirus or commit nineteen so and
as always we will have these links on
the episode page for Michelle's podcast
Thank You Michelle this has been
absolutely wonderful thank you
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]